Good morning everybody. Today's דף daf is נ''ט, Nun Tet, 59, and
we are finishing up a long סוגיא, sugya, hold your breath, we
will finish it today בלי נדר, bli neder, a long סוגיא sugya
on this issue about if something has a הלכתי halachic status, תרומה,
trumah, or ערלה, orlah, or we're going to finally get to our
משנה, mishnah, which is that it's אסור assur by a נדר, neder,
שמיטה, shmita, and then it continues to grow and the core is
still there like the case of the onion we've been focusing on,
does the additional amount that's grown, can that actually negate the core
that it originated from? Does the amount that's grown actually, does it
take on the same status? The גמרא Gemara seems to assume it
does not, seems to assume that the new stuff that grows would
be permissible, would have היתר heter status, let's say the שמיטה shmita
stuff continues to grow in the eighth year, but since in the
end it's just the same onion that got bigger, maybe there's no
way we should apply the laws of ביטול. bittul. This is the
question the גמרא Gemara asks, and we ended yesterday with a ברייתא
braita that pretty clearly spoke about this case about working in a
שמיטה shmita field after שמיטה, shmita, pulling up the weeds with somebody
who presumably planted שמיטה shmita produce and onions that are continuing to
grow. And the basic conclusion was was that the stuff was no
longer שמיטה, shmita, so that seems to conclusively prove that it changes
the status. And the גמרא Gemara said, well, maybe, maybe at least
it's true by שמיטה shmita because of the focus on the land.
So therefore the continued growth in the land can change the status.
And the way that I explained that was that by שמיטה shmita
the real question you ask yourself is, is this a seventh year
onion or an eighth year onion? So and if it's an eighth
year onion because most of it grew in the eighth year, then
it's permissible. So that might be enough by שמיטה, shmita, whereas if
it were a question about ערלה orlah or תרומה trumah or something
like that, then well, the onion started being ערלה, orlah, so now
it becomes much more of this question of and it's you know
the same onion, it doesn't just change its identity because it continues
to grow the same way maybe by שמיטה shmita it does. So
our question is still an open question whether the continued growth can
make it become permissible or not. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara at
least conceded the point by שמיטה. shmita. So now we pick up
at the top of נ''ט עמוד א', Nun Tet Amud Aleph, so
let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיב רמי
בר חמא, Metiv Rami Bar Chama, first line under the first line.
רמי
בר חמא Rami Bar Chama asks, קונם פירות האלו עלי. Konam peiros
ha-eilu alai.
Now we're finally, finally getting to our משנה. mishnah. Our משנה mishnah
says that if somebody makes a קונם, konam, a נדר, neder, using
the keyword קונם, konam, which is a euphemistic word and makes it
sort of like a קרבן, korban, and these fruits are forbidden to
me as a
קרבן, korban, קונם הן על פי konam hein al pi or to
my mouth,
קונם הן לפי, konam hein le-fi, different ways of saying they're forbidden,
but basically focusing not that you won't eat it or taste it,
but fundamentally that they're forbidden. So in those cases, אסור בחילופיהן ובגידוליהן,
assur be-chilofeihen u-ve-giduleihen, not only are the fruits forbidden, but any money
exchanged for the fruit is forbidden and anything that grows from the
fruit is forbidden. שאני אוכל, שאני טועם, She-ani ochel, she-ani toeim, if
however you said this is forbidden regarding eating or tasting, in that
case, מותר בחילופיהן ובגידוליהן, mutar be-chilofeihen u-ve-giduleihen, in that case we only
focus on the original fruit itself because it was not a more
generic forbidden, it was fundamentally focusing on the act of eating or
tasting, and that's not the same thing that that's not the same
act by the proceeds, you're not eating or tasting the fruit, and
even the stuff that continues to grow, well actually we're not excuse
me, because as we're going to see in a minute we're not
talking about the onion yet, we're talking about like let's say planting
seeds from wheat. So the new stuff that grew in its place
is not tasting or eating the old fruit because you planted a
seed and now you have new wheat. Okay, but here's that key
line: בדבר שזרעו כלה, Be-davar she-zaro kalah, that line, that idea that
it could be permissible with the new stuff is something that the
seed disintegrates, like you plant wheat seeds, so the new wheat that
grows has no part of the old wheat in it, and if
you use the more limited term שאני אוכל she-ani ochel
and שאני טועם, she-ani toeim, then the new wheat is totally okay.
However, אבל בדבר שאין זרעו כלה, aval be-davar she-ein zaro kalah, if
it is something that the original seed does not disintegrate, like the
onion case, in that case,
אפילו גידולי גידולים אסורים, afilu gidulei gidulim assurim,
even what grows from what grows is forbidden because there the original
thing is still present. So if you use this big powerful term
קונם konam and in a generic way, then it like goes way
beyond the it could go beyond the original fruit, right, it could
apply even to money exchanged for it, let alone to something that
grew from the seeds. That's not of interest to us, that might
be because the word קונם konam is a very broad word and
that doesn't prove cases where the focus is on the original object.
But here's the point that's relevant to us: even if you said
the more limited I won't eat and I won't taste from this
fruit, if you're dealing with something like an onion that the original
thing is still there and it continues to grow, then we
say. even though the onion continued to grow. Okay, that was great.
That was the משנה Mishna we said. That makes sense, because at
least part of the original onion is still there. Now there's just
more onion. The only problem is is that, but let's say it
grew a lot. Let's say the new amount, the new size of
it is much, much bigger than the original size. Why shouldn't we
apply the rules of ביטול? Bittul? Why shouldn't we say it's a
different onion? You know, apply the rules of nullification and of ביטול.
Bittul. So the fact that the משנה Mishna said the onion always
remains forbidden when it's something that, you know, the original part doesn't
disintegrate, the original part just expanded, shows that we don't say ביטול,
Bittul, right? Because it says that that original onion will always be
forbidden. So that should be a clear proof that we do not
say ביטול. Bittul. Is that clear to everybody? Yeah.
One thing can't be מבטל Mivatel itself.
Right, exactly. The continued growth of the same thing cannot be מבטל
Mivatel itself. Exactly. Okay, so that seems very clear from our משנה
Mishna and against what we said that by שמיטה Shmita it does,
that if it continues to grow in the eighth year we said
that it becomes an eighth year fruit. Here we see that it
seems like the general rule is is that you don't say ביטול,
Bittul, because otherwise the onion that grew should, there should be cases
where it should be permissible in the case of a נדר. Neder.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב אבא. Amar
Rav Abba.
Wait, I don't understand really גידול גידולים, Gidul Gidulim, right?
Let's, no, I'm not talking about גידול גידולים Gidul Gidulim now, let's
not confuse it, yes. We'll get to it later.
I don't understand how the ביטול Bittul issue came up in the
first place.
Well, the גמרא Gemara raised it as a conceptual question and ultimately
it's sourced in our, in our גמרא Gemara and in our משנה,
Mishna, because it's a relevant question to ask to our משנה. Mishna.
Why does the משנה Mishna say that if you make the onion
forbidden then, then it will always remain forbidden even if it continues
to grow? Let's say when I made it forbidden it was a
tiny little bulb and now it's ten times the size it was.
Well, why is it forbidden? Whatever happened to classic rules of ביטול?
Bittul? The new stuff that grew wasn't forbidden. Why can't it be
מבטל? Mivatel? So it's a perfect way of asking, well maybe you
don't say ביטול Bittul when it's the same thing that's growing. ביטול
Bittul normally is you take a little bit of חזיר Chazir and
it falls into your stew. But if it's the same thing that
expanded, that's exactly the גמרא's Gemara question. The משנה Mishna should show
that ביטול Bittul is not a relevant concept. Right, so let's take
a look at the answer. So אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba,
so רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said, you know what, you're right. ביטול
Bittul doesn't apply in our משנה, Mishna, but it's for a particular
reason.
שאני קונמות, Shani Konamos, so קונמות, Konamos, נדרים Nedarim are different. הואיל
ואית בי משאלה עליה, Ho-il ve-it bei mishala alai, so since you
can always ask about it, you can always, you know, go to
a חכם Chacham to be relieved from your vow, to be released
from your vow I should say. So therefore, הוי ליה, Havei lei,
well yes let's keep on reading, הוי ליה כדבר שיש לו מתירין.
Havei lei k'davar she'yesh lo matirin. It's like something that has a
way to become permissible, ואין בטל ברוב, ve-ein batel be-rov, and ביטול
Bittul doesn't apply. So, so basically what he is saying is you're
right, it's not בטל. Batel. But not because of something special of
the idea of a growing onion and it's the same thing. Even
if you took some of this little onion that was forbidden and
it dropped in your stew, right? So if it was חזיר Chazir
that dropped in your stew, it would be בטל. Batel. But if
it's this little onion that you made forbidden by a נדר Neder
and it dropped in your stew, it won't be בטל. Batel. Why?
Because of the principle that we introduced the other day, that דבר
שיש לו מתירין, Davar she'yesh lo matirin, something that is, will become
permissible or has a normal or natural way of becoming permissible, laws
of ביטול Bittul don't apply, just make it permissible, just do it
in a permissible way. By the way, the stew example is not
precise because דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar she'yesh lo matirin is not
בטל Batel is only when it's מין במינו. Min be-mino. Fine. But
anyway, this little bit of onion I took and I mixed up
into my whole big pile of onions that I got in the
store. All right, so even though normally that we would apply laws
of ביטול, Bittul, here we don't apply laws of ביטול Bittul because
it's a נדר Neder and a נדר Neder has a way of
becoming permissible.
Even though he may not permit.
Even though he might not, but there's a, and we'll see about
that in a minute. Okay, so it has nothing to do with
the mechanics of a growing onion. Growing onion maybe normal ביטול Bittul
applies. It has to do specifically with the status of it being
forbidden by virtue of a נדר. Neder. All right, so let's take
a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
Just one more formalistic response.
Well, they're both formalistic, it's just saying that it's based on a
different category. You're right, ביטול Bittul doesn't apply, but it's not because
of the, the laws of ביטול Bittul as it applies to growing
objects, it's the laws of ביטול Bittul as it applies to נדרים.
Nedarim.
But some things will be בטל Batel because מין שאינו מינו. Min
she-eino mino.
Yeah. So now the גמרא Gemara says, one minute. So now the
גמרא Gemara has the objection that Michael is saying, what, you mean
any time there's some way to change the status, even if it's
not the normal, we would say it's not בטל? Batel? והרי תרומה,
Ve-harei Teruma, how about תרומה? Teruma? דאי בעי משאלה עליה, De-ei bei
mishala alai,
תרומה Teruma is a, you know, we wouldn't normally put תרומה Teruma
in the same category of a נדר. Neder. תרומה Teruma is you're
obligated to separate off, you know, the amount from the grain to
the כהן. Kohen. You say this is תרומה, Teruma, this is מעשר
Ma'aser and so on. But because that's a status that gets effected
through your speech act, right you don't have to physically separate it,
you can just
verbal Remember, classic נדר neder is about changing the status of an
object, and it's learned from, you know, or as the word קונם,
konam, from like the world of קרבנות. korbanot. You take your little
your sheep and you say this is a קרבן. korban. So I
could say this fruit is forbidden like a קרבן, korban, this sheep
is a קרבן. korban. So it's not primarily about making things forbidden.
If you think about it, what it's really rooted in is the
power of your speech act to impart a halakhic status on an
object. And therefore, תרומה truma and מעשר ma'aser is the same thing.
You use your speech act, you make this grain תרומה, truma, and
therefore, it's if you went to a חכם, chacham, the same way
you could be released from a נדר, neder, you could say, "You
know what, I had never meant to make that grain תרומה." truma.
Okay, so somehow we can free you from that. The same way
you can be freed from a נדר neder and retroactively if you've
been eating from that grain you wouldn't be eating טבל, tevel, right.
But you can be free the same way actually you could go
to a חכם chacham in some cases and if I made the
animal a קרבן korban before I brought it up on the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I
would say I want to exchange it, but that's תמורה, tmura, then
you'd be trans... but if you go to a חכם, chacham, it
could be released from that, he could negate the speech act and
then it would be like it never took place. So הקדש, hekdesh,
yeah, so הקדש, hekdesh, it's pretty amazing, right? The speech act is
such this like this like non-physical act that has this tremendous power,
right? It could be transform, it could make basically create an entire
religious world, make things הקדש, hekdesh, make things קרבנות, korbanos, make things
תרומה, truma, make things forbidden by נדרים. nedarim. But also somehow because
it's rooted in just speech and speech seems to be rooted also
in will and in thought, right? In that way speech is different.
It's an expression of will and thought as opposed to something which
is like a physical reality. So the releasing of the vow is
basically a process of saying, "Well, deep down you really didn't want
it," right? That's sort of what the releasing of the vow is.
So it's this amazing thing that on one hand it's so tremendously
powerful, just the speech act, and on the other hand it has
this it has this like doorway, this avenue, to completely undo it
because deep down it's rooted in your will and your thought. Yes,
Charlie.
So for תרומה, truma, if I get my separation of תרומה truma
and designation nullified, it not only affects the תרומה, truma, it affects
everything else.
That's what Michael was saying, then the grain retroactively becomes טבל, tevel,
yeah. So you wouldn't want to do that if you've been eating
from the grain. That is correct, yes.
Does it parallel to השם Hashem spoke and the world was created
in the sense of the power of speech?
Right, that's an excellent point, right? I mean, in a way it's
like the most divine sort of thing, you know, just purely by
speech is where we can imitate God. You don't even have to
interact physically with the
world.
Yes. I'll take a little different angle, God's speech creates the whole
world of
obligation by
commands you mean, and
also the interpretation of that speech is kind of rabbinic, תורה שבעל
פה.
Torah she-ba'al peh.
Kind of parallel to but "what I really mean when I said
it."
Oh, you mean sort of oh, you know, there's actually some מדרשים
midrashim like that about how God goes to I forget what the
מדרש midrash is but like God goes to אברהם Avraham or יצחק
Yitzchak in a certain case and he asks to be released from
his נדר, neder, like God asks to be I forget what the
נדר neder is. But that's an interesting idea like תורה שבעל פה
Torah she-ba'al peh is the rabbis acting like בית דין beis din
on God's word to interpret what God's word means. That's a great
idea. That's beautiful. Okay. Alright, good. We now we've got enough theology
for the rest of the מסכת. masechet. Okay, so alright, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, it says, והרי תרומה, Va-harei truma,
how about תרומה? truma? דאי בעי מתשיל עלה, de-ei ba'ei metashil alah,
if you want you could ask, meaning ask about it, meaning go
and get released from
it. וביטלה, ubetlah, and תרומה truma is בטלה—some batel take out the
word ברוב berov because it's not exactly by a רוב—but rov it
is בטלה. batel. Yeah, exactly, 100%. But it's בטלה. batel. So we
don't treat it as a דבר שיש לו מתירין, davar she-yesh lo
matirin, right? Even though there's a way to reverse it, we treat
תרומה truma as תרומה truma and תרומה truma as איסור issur and
it's בטלה. batel. דתנן, de-tnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, סאה
תרומה טמאה, se'ah truma tmeiah, if you have a סאה, se'ah, whatever,
a unit of תרומה truma טמאה, tmeiah, that it's impure, so actually
even a כהן Kohen can't eat it, it has to be burned,
שנפלה לפחות ממאה חולין, she-nafla le-pachot mi-me'ah chullin, if it falls into
a mixture of less than a hundred units of חולין, chullin, so
it's not enough to do ביטול, bittul, תרומה truma needs a hundred
to do ביטול, bittul, תרקב, tirakev,
let it rot. הא למאה, ha le-me'ah, implicit says the גמרא, Gemara,
if it fell into a hundred, תעלה, ta'aleh, then it is nullified
and it's okay. So you see that you have principles of ביטול
bittul by תרומה. truma. Why don't we treat it like a דבר
שיש לו מתירין? davar she-yesh lo matirin? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמרי, amri, you can say, בתרומה ביד כהן עסקינן, be-truma beyad Kohen
askinan, the case when ביטול bittul applies by תרומה truma is that
you've already given it to a כהן. Kohen. Once you've already given
it to a כהן, Kohen, דלא מצי מתשיל עליה, de-lo matzi metashil
alei, you can no longer reverse it, because then in a way
your words have had a real-world impact. Right now somebody else also's
involved. It's not just the... between you and God and your speech
and the object. It actually now has impli—now another person owns it
and you're going to be taking the תרומה Trumah out of his
hand and saying, "Sorry bud, I know I gave it to you,
but it's no longer תרומה," Trumah, and take it away. So now
that it's actually had a real world impact and it's involved another
person, you can no longer reverse it by going to a חכם.
Chacham. So therefore the גמרא Gemara says maybe before you've given תרומה
Trumah to a כהן Kohen and you can reverse it, maybe no
ביטול Bittul would apply. And maybe whenever we discuss ביטול Bittul by
תרומה, Trumah, it's only after it's been given to a כהן. Kohen.
So that's a significant limiting on the laws of ביטול Bittul and
the גמרא Gemara rejects that. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. So the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי I hachi if that's true, אמא סיפא, Eima seifa, look at
the end of that of that
משנה. Mishna. אם הייתה טהורה, Im hayeta tehorah, if it was טהורה
Tehorah תרומה Trumah that got mixed up, so if it's טהורה Tehorah
תרומה Trumah it doesn't have to be burnt, it can be eaten
by a כהן. Kohen. So טהורה Tehorah תרומה Trumah got mixed up
in this mixture, not enough to create ביטול, Bittul, what do you
do with this mixture? תמכר לכהן. Timacher l'Kohen. So sell it to
a כהן. Kohen. So it's clear that the תרומה Trumah has yet
to be given to a כהן, Kohen, right? You have a mixture,
you have one unit of תרומה Trumah getting mixed up in ninety-nine
units of non-תרומה. Trumah. So what can you do with it? You
can't eat it 'cause you're not a כהן. Kohen. But a כהן
Kohen could eat it, it's just got a little תרומה Trumah mixed.
So you don't want to just סתם Stam give the כהן Kohen
a hundred units of grain, I mean you know, you want to
at least salvage some money out of it. So you sell it
to the כהן, Kohen, but the כהן's Kohen got you over a
barrel 'cause the כהן's Kohen going to say, "I'm not going to
pay you the going rate for that grain, I'm only going to
pay you the תרומה Trumah rate for that grain." Okay, so he
now gets this whole thing, right? because you know, you have no
choice. So that's what it says you do. Fine, find a כהן,
Kohen, sell it to him, the כהן Kohen gets to eat the
תרומה, Trumah, you at least get to salvage some money from it.
So what do you see? You see we're talking that it's not
yet in the hands of a כהן, Kohen, it's in your hands.
And nevertheless, if it were in a hundred, ביטול Bittul would apply.
So we're back to this reality that ביטול Bittul applies by תרומה.
Trumah. Why is that if it's to be considered a דבר שיש
לו מתירין? Davar she-yesh lo matirin? So the גמרא Gemara let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא בישראל,
Ella b'Yisrael, fine it is a ישראל Yisrael that owns the תרומה,
Trumah, not a כהן, Kohen, but we're still going to say that
it's too late to reverse it. Why is it too late to
reverse it? שנפלו לו מבית אבי אמו כהן עסקינן. She-naflu lo mibeit
avi imo Kohen askinan. Yes, it's a ישראל Yisrael that has the
תרומה, Trumah, but it's תרומה Trumah that's already been given to a
כהן. Kohen. How could the ישראל Yisrael have the תרומה Trumah if
it's already been given to a כהן? Kohen? Because it was given
to a כהן Kohen ten years ago. Who was this כהן? Kohen?
It was his maternal grandfather. That's why he's not a כהן, Kohen,
but his grandfather, right, his his grandfather on his mother's side is
a כהן. Kohen. So he got this תרומה Trumah as an inheritance.
I hope it's still edible, from his maternal grandfather, it was תרומה
Trumah that had been given ten years ago, twenty years ago to
a כהן, Kohen, but now he owns it. I mean a simpler
case would be a כהן Kohen friend of his said, "Look, here's
a gift, here, take all my תרומה." Trumah. Now that would be
a funnier case. What am I going to do with your תרומה?
Trumah? I can't eat it. But the point is it was given
to a כהן Kohen but now he owns it. So in that
case because it was given to a כהן Kohen many years ago,
it can never be reversed, but but it's a scenario that he
owns it so the משנה Mishna could say if it gets mixed
up, find another כהן Kohen to sell it to. Okay, so let's
take a look.
Simpler case would be the daughter of a כהן, Kohen, right? But
we don't talk about women.
Oh, you mean it was a woman that actually was owning it.
Right, that would be true, exactly. Okay, so הכי קתני סיפא, Hak-tani
seifa, the גמרא Gemara says one minute. The end of it says,
תמכר לכהן, Timacher l'Kohen, if you have to sell this mixture to
a כהן, Kohen, sell it to the כהן, Kohen, חוץ מדמי אותה
סאה. Chutz midmei otah se'ah. You got one unit of תרומה Trumah
mixed up with ninety-nine units of non-תרומה. Trumah. You have to sell
it to a כהן. Kohen. Can I charge him for a hundred
units or only for ninety-nine? Well, yes, but that's true, I mean
you could sort of say whatever whatever arrangement you make. But you
have to be clear that whatever price you agree upon, the price
does not include the one סאה Se'ah of תרומה, Trumah, the price
is for the other ninety-nine. Why? 'Cause I'm not entitled to sell
him the one סאה Se'ah of תרומה, Trumah, I have an obligation
to give him the one סאה Se'ah of תרומה. Trumah. So you're
right, it's not telling you what you charge, but telling you the
way you frame what you charge is that I'm charging you for
the ninety-nine of חולין, Chullin, I'm not charging you for the one
of תרומה, Trumah, I'm not allowed to charge you for the one
of תרומה, Trumah, that has to be my gift to you. So
that shows that it was never given to a כהן, Kohen, 'cause
if it was given to his grandfather the כהן, Kohen, then he
fully owns it, he's allowed to resell it to a כהן. Kohen.
So it has to be תרומה Trumah that has never been given,
and because it's never been given he has to give it to
a כהן Kohen he's not allowed to charge for it. So it's
clear from the משנה Mishna that we are dealing with a case
of a simple case that it's a ישראל Yisrael who separated תרומה
Trumah from his grain, it's never been given to a כהן, Kohen,
it gets mixed up with other grain and the משנה Mishna says
that it's בטל. Battel. So says the גמרא, Gemara, why is it
בטל? Battel? It's never been given to a כהן, Kohen, why don't
we say according to your logic that it should It's a דבר
שיש לו מתירין, Davar sheyesh lo matirin, you could always reverse it
and shouldn't be בטל. Batel. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara
answer is. So it says אלא אימא, Ela eima, here's what you
should say: בשלמא קונמות, Bishlama konamot, we're going to stick by our
idea that a נדר Neder is a יש לו מתירין, yesh lo
matirin, but it's only by a נדר. neder. נדר Neder makes sense
that it's considered יש לו מתירין, yesh lo matirin, you could always
go to a get it reversed, get release. Why?
מצוה לאיתשולי עלייהו. Mitzvah le'itshulei aleihu. It's a מצוה mitzvah to be
released from your vow. How do you know that? משום דרבי נתן
Mishum deRabbi Natan because of Rabbi
Natan, דאמר רבי נתן De'amar Rabbi Natan Rabbi Natan says:
כל הנודר כאילו בנה במה. Kol hanoder ke'ilu bana bamah. Anybody who
makes a vow is like building a במה. bamah. Building a במה
bamah is not a good thing if there's a בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, you're not allowed to. So in your mind you're trying to
worship God. What are you giving me a hard time, I'm building
an altar, not to some idol, to God, in my backyard. That's
a good thing, right? So he says no, and that's what a
נדר neder is. Hey, I'm trying to do more מצוות, mitzvot, I'm
trying to increase my world of religious objects, right? I'm trying to
make things forbidden and so on. God makes things forbidden, says חזיר
ובשר בחלב, Chazir uvasar bechalav, I'm going to continue and I'm going
to make the fruit forbidden and all these things. Isn't this a
good thing? Right, that's like a חומרא chumra attitude. And the גמרא
Gemara says, you know what that says, that's your private religion, okay?
That's like building a במה. bamah. So your private religious experience and
you know what, that's not necessarily a good thing, meaning maybe there's
times when it is good to build a במה, bamah, if there's
no בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right? Maybe if there's no good, you
know, maybe if there's a problem with establishment religion or there's no
good sort of central religious experience or communal religious experience, maybe we
understand and can give more latitude towards these personal desires for creating
their own religious reality. But at least Rabbi Natan says, you know,
that's generally that's basically not a good thing. You know, that's not
our religious experience is supposed to be a communal one, not every
private person sort of, you know, trying to create their own religious
reality. And therefore making a נדר neder is like building a במה.
bamah. Now he goes further. Building a במה bamah is not yet
so bad, I just built it, it's just my intention, I haven't
yet done anything with the במה. bamah. So then he says והמקיימו,
Vehamkayemo, if you take it to the next step and you haven't
only made the נדר, neder, but rather than knocking down the במה
bamah and going to a חכם Chacham and being released from it,
you actually took it to the next step and you fulfilled the
נדר. neder. In that case he says כאילו הקריב עליו, Ke'ilu hikriv
alav, ומקטיר עליה, Umaktir aleha,
it's like you burnt incense on the במה. bamah. That makes it
even worse because now you finally you acted on it and you
lived that experience and you had an option of being released from
it. Okay, so this is a quite scathing condemnation of the entire
מסכת. masechet. And the fascinating thing is, is that the גמרא Gemara
quotes Rabbi Natan time and time again. Like if you just look
at the side, I mean one, two, three, four, up to only
four times, to me it felt like it was more. But anyway,
but the גמרא, Gemara, you know, it very much reiterates this critique
and really doesn't give that much voice to a more positive approach.
And what's clear is, and we discussed this at the beginning of
the מסכת, masechet, that making vows was a very widespread phenomenon in
the community. You know, too widespread. People were making them and just
very loosely without giving them enough weight and so on. And it's
A, part of what the purpose of מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim is,
is to try to get control over that phenomenon. Not, you know,
to sort of say not all these things are binding and you
have to be more careful about the process and so on. But
also, at least Rabbi Natan and something that seems to be pretty
much endorsed by the גמרא Gemara seems to have a very like
scathing critique of the whole thing as a religious as a positive
religious phenomenon altogether. One minute. So because of this approach that this
whole thing is a bad phenomenon, we say if you made a
נדר, neder, you know why it's a דבר שיש לו מתירין? davar
sheyesh lo matirin? Because you're supposed to get it undone. And therefore
because you're obligated and supposed to get it undone, it's like it's
היתר heter right now. Why should we say apply the laws of
ביטול, bitul, we would rather tell you go to a חכם, Chacham,
get it undone, that's what you're supposed to have done in the
first place, and then you don't need to rely on the laws
of ביטול. bitul. So by נדרים nedarim there's no ביטול bitul because
you're supposed to reverse it. Whereas by תרומה terumah you're not supposed
to reverse it. You're supposed to separate תרומה terumah and give it
to a כהן kohen and therefore we don't treat it, even though
in theory you could reverse it, that's not what you're supposed to
do, and we don't treat it as a דבר שיש לו מתירין.
davar sheyesh lo matirin. Okay, question.
Sorry, let's just one more line. תרומה מאי מצוה לאיתשולי עלה? Terumah
mai mitzvah le'itshulei alah? But by תרומה terumah there's no מצוה mitzvah
to get it reversed. The opposite. By תרומה terumah you make תרומה
terumah and there's a מצוה mitzvah to keep it as תרומה terumah
and to go ahead and give it, so תרומה terumah is not
a דבר שיש לו מתירין, davar sheyesh lo matirin, נדר neder is.
Rachel you had a question.
I did. So I think this speaks to, so this is contextualizing
the whole discussion, but is part of why we're agonizing over all
these details a way to make it more complicated as a deterrent
against נדר? neder?
Yeah, so that is something that we spoke about at the beginning
and Saul Lieberman, the great scholar from the previous generation, had a
whole essay about this about how... widespread vows were in the general
Greco-Roman world and how trivialized they had become not just within the
Jewish community and that it seems very clear that a lot of
what the rabbis are trying to do here is take control over
that
phenomenon and to have it be a deterrent, have people treat it
more weightily, have people not let it get as run and be
runaway. On the one hand when you take it you have to
be serious about it and the other hand we would like you
to stop taking it all together. Yes.
But it's not only to take it seriously, it's to show the
impossibility really of starting to take vows.
Well I don't know, I mean like any other area of הלכה,
Halakha, just because it's complicated and there are a lot of details
doesn't mean we're trying to say it's impossible. So I don't think
the rabbis are sort of saying like we can't figure out what
you're doing don't do it at all. That happened at a later
stage; there became in the time of the גאונים Geonim a practice
not to study מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim as a way of like
we should keep everybody ignorant about it so that they won't be
doing it. The more you learn about it the more it's a
live possibility and the more you think you can handle it and
know what the parameters are. So that became like a later point;
let's just not learn it to sort of make it off-limits. But
I wouldn't say that the גמרא Gemara is trying to make it,
I mean maybe it feels that way to us, but everything it
makes complicated it makes a lot of details. I don't see the
details as a deterrent per se.
No, just the touching upon so many other different areas. So in
other words on the one hand you're emphasizing the power of language,
right, but it's not only the language you intend, it's all the
things that you may be unaware of what you're doing. Right. So
it's sort of words are linked with intention. Right.
If you don't know what you're saying then, right,
you could just happen to adverse.
Right, right, I agree. And but I think that that's all just
tying into how serious and complicated this is. Right. I think that's
all giving like this thing weight and meaning you have to take
this extremely sort of thoughtfully and seriously. Yes Charlie.
At one point everybody was building במות bamot all over the place,
exactly,
and it took hundreds of years to get
rid of them even when things were better. Right. So yeah and
that's you know you could say there are times maybe when במות
bamot are
appropriate but they also very hard to uproot or you sort of
saying the proliferation of נדרים nedarim is very hard to uproot and
whole personal rite. And then you also right give wind up giving
disproportionate weight to all of your little sort of
personalized all the מנהגים minhagim wind up picking up more weight than
all like the איסורי דאורייתא issurei d'oraitsa type of a thing, you
know. So exactly.
Is it possible that the משנה Mishnah and the גמרא Gemara have
in some ways different agendas? In other words that ביטול bitul doesn't
appear in the משנה. Mishnah. Right. It's clear the משנה Mishnah is
not talking about a gift from my maternal father.
Well that was right, the גמרא Gemara conceived of it, well that's
yes but that's true in general you know that the גמרא Gemara
raises new issues and tries to reframe things and that's not necessarily
the פשט. pshat. Right. Correct.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so that was
really very fascinating in terms of reminding us of this sort of
scathing critique of רבי נתן Rabbi Natan and that's how we explain
in the משנה Mishnah why ביטול bitul does not apply because we'd
rather you just reversed your vow. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. גופא, Gufa, let's get back to the original statement.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, ליטרא בצלים שתיקנה וזרעה, litra betzalim
shetinkna vizarah,
you have a liter of onions that you took תרומות ומעשרות trumot
u'maasrot and then you went ahead and you planted it. Okay and
these onions continued to grow. מתעשרת לפי כולה. mitaseret lefi kulah. You
take מעשר ma'aser according to the total amount that onions that are
there. You don't deduct, you don't say now I have ten liters
of onions I'll take you know you'll say but one minute there
was one liter that was originally there that I planted I should
only be taking תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot from nine units not from
ten units because one unit was already taken care of in terms
of תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot right do you understand the scenario? So
why is it that you take all ten units? So this again
indicates that this idea of ביטול bitul applies and therefore you know
the whole thing is now redefined by the new growth by the
majority. So the
גמרא Gemara says okay so יתיב רבה, yativ Rabbah, so or רבא,
Rava, have some have the גירסא girsa וקאמרי להא שמעתא v'kamrei l'hashma'ata
was telling over this discussion and this idea that you take תרומות
ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot according to the total amount the ten units. אמר
ליה רב חסדא, Amar lei Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda said
to him, מאן ציית לך ולרבי יוחנן רבך? man tsayeis lach u'l'Rabbi
Yochanan rabach? Who's going to listen to you or רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan your רבי rebbe because he said this in the name of
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Who's who would listen to such a crazy
statement? היתר שבהן להיכן הלך? heter shebahen leheichan halach? Where did the
היתר heter disappear to? Where did that original unit disappear? Now what
exactly is bothering him? Has he never heard of the idea of
ביטול? bitul? If I take a little חזיר chazir and I drop
it in my soup do we say well where did the חזיר
chazir disappear to? Oh what do you mean where did it disappear?
That's what ביטול bitul is. ביטול bitul nullifies it and makes it
like it doesn't exist. So here... Where do the new nine units
nullify the original one unit? What's your question? So it seems like
this question is the following. רן Ran explains it in a similar
way, but a little different, is that ביטול bittul normally works by
erasing something's distinctive halachic status. I've got חזיר, chazer, חזיר chazer is
אסור, assur, it falls into my stew, the איסור issur status goes
away. It's just a neutral piece of meat now, it's not an
אסור assur piece of meat. Okay? But can, can ביטול bittul work
not to erase a status but to impart a status? Like one
of the אחרונים achronim asks the following question. Let's say I've got,
I don't know, nine מזוזות mezuzos here and they're all written properly
with the right intention of שם השם shem Hashem when the סופר
sofer was writing it, and one מזוזה mezuza was written without the
right intention. Okay? The סופר sofer wasn't thinking about God's name when
he wrote God's name, or whatever, and I mix up that מזוזה
mezuza and the other nine. Are all ten כשר kosher now? Right?
Is that how ביטול bittul works? Right? Does ביטול bittul say that
I actually can impart a status onto an object or it just
means that if an object has some type of a problematic status,
that status gets erased? That seems to be what he's saying. He's
saying here ביטול bittul is taking היתר, heter, that original unit that
had a neutral status, it was all fine, it was all fixed,
and it's turning it into טבל. tevel. Because if you take תרומות
terumos and מעשרות ma'asros from all ten units, you're saying you have
ten units of טבל. tevel. So you took that one unit that
was totally neutral and you turned it into טבל. tevel. That's normally
not how ביטול bittul works. Okay? So that's a really fascinating question.
Can ביטול bittul go ahead and take something, take היתר heter and
make היתר heter into איסור issur almost, or to make היתר heter
into, impart a halachic status on an object?
Yes? Has something to do with ביטול? bittul? I mean when you
take the bulb and plant it, maybe you're changing its identity from
produce to seed.
Ah, so that is an excellent point and that's what it gets
to the question all along: Why did the מרשיק Marsic think that
ביטול bittul wouldn't work, why would it work? Maybe this whole thing
is seen as more like transformative than just the same plus. So
we'll get to an answer very similar to that. But let's first
appreciate what the question is. Okay, let's see, so I framed it
as a question about: can ביטול bittul take היתר heter and give
היתר heter a, add a status as opposed to remove a status?
Let's just read the רן. Ran. The רן Ran is similar but
a little different.
והיא חדא להיכן אזלא Vehei chada l'heichan azla means where'd it come
from?
No, where'd it go to? This first unit was היתר. heter. You've
now made it no longer היתר. heter. You've made it into
טבל. tevel.
How did you, what happened to its היתר heter status?
Exactly. Because you've now used ביטול bittul to make something אסור. assur.
We normally use ביטול bittul to make something היתר. heter. Okay, so
let's see the רן. Ran. וכי היתר שבהם היכן הלך, Vechi heter
shebahem heichan halach, five lines from the bottom.
נראה בעיני Nireh be'einai says the רן, Ran, it seems to me,
דהכי מקשה, de'hachi maksha, here's the question. אפילו תימא דגידולים של היתר
מבטלין עיקר, Afillu teima degidulim shel heter mevatlin ikar, even if normally
you say that there is an idea of ביטול bittul by the
stuff that continues to grow, של איסור, shel issur, that's when it's
מבטל mevatel the original amount that's forbidden and the new stuff negates
it, nullifies it. התם היינו טעמא, Hatam hainu ta'ama, משום דכיון שרבו
גידוליו על עיקרו, mishum dekivan sherabu gidulav al ikaro, since there's now
the amount, the new stuff is more than the
original, נמצא כשאוכל אינו טועם טעם האיסור, nimtza keshe'ochel eino to'em ta'am
ha'issur, so you're no longer tasting the taste of the original thing
which was forbidden. So if you don't have the taste of anything
forbidden it's okay, כלל. klal. הילכך אף על פי שאיסור שבו מעורב
בתוכו, Hilkach af al pi she'issur shebo me'urav betocho, therefore even though
some of the original onion is still there, ולא אזלא ליה לעלמא,
velo azla leh l'alma, it hasn't really disappeared, you have some of
the original onion there, שרי, shari, it's permissible.
אבל גבי מעשר, Aval gabai ma'aser, כיון דלפי חשבון הטבל חייבה רחמנא
לאסורו, kivan de'lefi cheshbon hatevel chiyvei rachamana le'asuro, since the תורה Torah
obligated you according to the actual quantity, אמאי מתעשר לפי כולו, amai
mit'aser lefi kulo, why is it go by the full amount, וכי
היתר שבהם היכן הלך, vechi heter shebahem heichan halach, where did the
היתר heter go? So it's not fully clear what he's saying. It
seems like what he's saying is something of the following,
and this is another question by ביטול. bittul. When we say that
חזיר chazer fell into the soup, okay, do we say that I
no longer have חזיר chazer here or do we say I have
חזיר chazer but it's not אסור? assur? If I can't taste it,
it's not אסור. assur. If I can't see it, I can't taste
it, I can't identify it even though there's חזיר chazer here it's
not אסור. assur. That seems to be what he's saying. We don't
say that the thing disappears. We don't say it stops being חזיר,
chazer, we just say that its prohibition goes away if it can't
be tasted. But if it didn't disappear, if it's still there, so
here you only, you have only nine new units. You have one
old unit. So how are you taking תרומות terumos and מעשרות ma'asros
on ten units if you really only have nine new units?
Why have it on the עיקר?
ikar? No, yeah that is getting into the points. But anyway I
think the easier way of understanding the question is, since when does
ביטול bittul make היתר heter into איסור? issur? ביטול bittul removes an
איסור, issur, it does not make something into an איסור, issur, it
does not make this original unit into טבל. tevel. Okay? So that's
a really nice conceptual question. Let's see what he says. אמר ליה,
Amaleh, so he said back to him, מי לא תנן דכוותיה, mi
lo t'nas d'chavateih, what do you mean? I'll show you a משנה.
mishna. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said
back to him, מי לא תניא כוותיה דכוותיה, Mi lo tanya kavatei
dechvatei, what do you mean? I'll show you a משנה Mishna that's
like this. בצלים שירדו עליהם גשמים וצמחו. Batzalim sheyardu aleihem geshamim v'tzimchehu.
We quoted this before. You have these onions that was rained on,
that they came from the sixth year, and then it was rained
and they continued to grow in the seventh year. אם היו עלין
שלהן שחורין, Im hayu alin shelahen shchorin, if the leaves were black,
אסורין, assurin, it's forbidden because then it's considered to have grown in
the seventh year. הוריקו מותרין, Horiku mutarin, but if they turned green
then it's permissible, it all grew in the sixth year. Now, we
did this yesterday. וכי שחורין, V'chi shchorin, now if the leaves are
black, אמאי אסורין, amai assurin, why is the whole onion forbidden? Some
new amount grew, but some of this onion was from the sixth
year. And the language that the onion is forbidden makes it sound
like the whole onion is forbidden. Now, what would be the relevance?
You can't find, separate off the different parts of the onion. Well,
one relevance is is that by שמיטה, shmita, if I sell שמיטה
shmita produce, the money I get for it also gets the status
of שמיטה. shmita. So let's say I've got this onion, right? 20%
grew in the sixth year and 80% grew in the seventh year,
and I sell it for a dollar. How much of that dollar
has קדושת שביעית? kedushat shvi'it? 80 cents or the whole dollar's worth?
All right, because only 20% of it grew in the sixth year.
So the language that the onion is אסור assur sounds like the
whole onion is אסור. assur. So he's saying same question.
If ביטול bitul does not work to make היתר heter into איסור,
issur, why is the whole onion אסור? assur? Only 80% of the
onion should be אסור. assur. And the language of the משנה Mishna
sounds like the whole onion is שמיטה. shmita. Okay, so it's same
question. When can ביטול bitul work to turn היתר heter into איסור?
issur? Okay, yes.
Isn't the underlying principle of ביטול bitul that it becomes indistinguishable from
the רוב rov in which it's mixed? Yes. So therefore the ליטרא
litra of onions which was טבל tevel already, which had מעשר, ma'aser,
when it's mixed in the other nine becomes indistinguishable from the whole
thing.
Yeah, it's indistinguishable, but
now it has to be treated like the whole thing?
No, because still if you know that 10%, if you know that
only nine units, you can't separate out. You don't know which is
which. There's no way to distinguish. That's true. But you know as
a, that only nine units here are טבל, tevel, then when you
figure out how much תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot you have to take,
you should be taking according to nine units, right? I can't eat
any of it because I can't find the right part. Let's say,
let's say here, let's say it was a question of ownership. I
had nine units of my onions, you had one unit of your
onion got mixed up in nine units of mine. Should I say,
well, since we can't distinguish it, I'll just take it all? No,
I'd have to pay you for your one unit, right?
But by your logic even when you have ביטול bitul you should
have to scoop out one sixtieth of your soup and throw it
away.
Which is why we don't just say it's indistinguishable by ביטול, bitul,
what we actually say is is that it's nullified, its הלכה halacha
status gets erased. So if we say that the הלכה halacha status
gets erased, the question is well that's when it's about erasing a
הלכה halacha status. Here it seems like we're imparting a הלכה halacha
status. Do you say that also by ביטול? bitul? That's the question.
So it says, look, it seems like the whole onion has שמיטה
shmita status, so it does seem like we actually, you know, transformed
the sixth year's part of the onion into seventh year onion. That's
taking something that was מותר mutar and making it אסור. assur. Exactly.
Which is the point that they want to prove. Exactly. So he's
saying maybe it's other work. וכי שחורין אמאי אסורין, V'chi shchorin amai
assurin, why even if the leaves are black is the whole onion
forbidden? לימא היתר שבהן היכן הלך, Leima heter shebahen heichan halach, say
what happened to the part of this onion that grew in the
sixth year? So it actually seems that when you say ביטול, bitul,
even the stuff that's permissible becomes אסור. assur. Really gets, you know,
not just we erase a status, we can impart a status.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, מי סברת
אעיקר
קתני, mi savrat a'ikar katani,
when it says the onion is forbidden, what makes you think we're
talking even about the original part of the onion? אתוספת קתני, A'tosefet
katani, we're only talking about the new part that grew. The new
part of the onion is forbidden, the original is permissible. It's all
mixed up, you can't distinguish, אגב אורחיה, agav orchiah,
but nevertheless, okay, so you can't eat any part of or whatever,
you have to treat the whole onion like שמיטה, shmita, but the
reality is only 80% of it really is שמיטה, shmita, 20% is
not. אתוספת קתני אסורין,
A'tosefet
katani
assurin, right, we're only saying that the new stuff is אסור. assur.
We're not saying the old stuff became אסור. assur. The גמרא Gemara
says one minute, אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, מאי אתא
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל למימר, mai ata Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel l'meimar,
what does רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel coming to
add to that statement? דתניא, Detanya, as we saw in a ברייתא
braita that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel has the
following sort of reflection on the משנה. Mishna. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says in this case of the onion that grew from
the sixth year to the seventh year, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, הגדל בחיוב חייב, hagadel b'chiyuv chayav, the
stuff that grew in the seventh year is חייב, chayav, you know,
has the sort of status of שמיטה. shmita. הגדל בפטור פטור, Hagadel
b'pator pator, the stuff that grew in the exempt period of time
is exempt. So it seems like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel is saying only the new stuff is שמיטה, shmita, not
the old stuff. That's what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel saying.
So it sounds like he's talking about the
entire...
No, no, no, it's the opposite. He's saying that part that grew
during the היתר Heter time remains היתר, Heter, the part that grew
during the אסור Assur time becomes אסור. Assur. He's saying don't say
the whole thing has one status. How do you תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma say the whole onion is אסור? Assur? It's not the whole
onion is אסור. Assur. The part that grew during the איסור Issur
period is אסור, Assur, the part that grew during the היתר Heter
period is היתר. Heter. Like it sounds like this is an exact
debate of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel.
Do people see that? Yes? Right. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma uses
the phrase about this onion that grew part in year six and
part in year seven. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says אסור. Assur.
And רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says, how can you say אסור? Assur?
The part from the of the sixth year is מותר, Mutar, the
part of the seventh year is אסור, Assur, and it's all mixed
together. So the גמרא Gemara says, so it sounds like the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma is saying it all becomes אסור Assur and ביטול
Bittul works to transform היתר Heter into איסור. Issur. Alright. So the
גמרא Gemara says, תנא קמא נמי הכי אמר, Tanna Kamma Nami Hachi
Amar, according to you, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is also just
referring to the new stuff. Okay. So it doesn't sound like that.
It sounds like the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma because רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel is distinguishing between the old and the new, it sounds like
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying that it all becomes אסור. Assur.
And that proves my point that ביטול Bittul can work even that
way. So the גמרא Gemara says, מתניתין רבי שמעון בן גמליאל קתני
לה. Matnitin Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel Katani Lah.
You know what? Our משנה Mishna really, when the ברייתא Baraita has
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel saying that old and new, our משנה Mishna
is no different than רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. Our משנה Mishna is
also the position of רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. He's clarifying in the
ברייתא Baraita what he meant, but the משנה Mishna really is not
a different opinion. ועד כאן לא שמיע ליה לרבי שמעון בן גמליאל,
V'Ad Kan Lo Shami'a Lei L'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, okay. So basically,
so now what does the גמרא Gemara say? The גמרא Gemara says
like this. The question is when you have ביטול Bittul and the
majority is the original stuff, the minority is a neutral halakhic status
is היתר, Heter, and now you have a majority that's a new
problematic halakhic status, does it even transform the היתר? Heter? Does it
make that one unit into טבל Tevel if the new stuff is
טבל? Tevel? Does it make that one unit that grew in the
sixth year into שמיטה Shmita if the new stuff is שמיטה? Shmita?
Does it transform, does it not just erase a status but impart
one? So the initial statement was yes, it does erase a status,
that's what happens in the טבל Tevel case. I mean, not actually,
yes, it does impart a new status, that's what happens in the
טבל Tevel case. And that
and maybe that seems to be what's happening in this case here
by the onion that grew in the sixth year and the seventh
year. Maybe the whole onion becomes becomes שמיטה. Shmita. And the גמרא
Gemara says wait wait wait, not so, you know, maybe not. Maybe
where it says that we treat the onion as שמיטה, Shmita, maybe
that's just the position of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and maybe it
means the new stuff is שמיטה Shmita not the old stuff. Okay?
So in this case where it says that we treat this onion
as שמיטה, Shmita, it's not clear if we're saying that that applies
to the whole onion or just to the new part of the
onion. And here the גמרא Gemara says maybe this question of whether
it transforms that original status or not, maybe maybe some of the
particulars matter. And Dov, this gets to the point you were making
before. So let's see what it says.
ועד כאן לא שמיע ליה לרבי שמעון בן גמליאל דלא טרח. V'Ad
Kan Lo Shami'a Lei L'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel d'Lo Tarach. Maybe רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, who we're now claiming is the author of the
whole משנה, Mishna, that says that the new status only applies to
the new stuff, not to the old stuff. Maybe that's only when
you did not exert any effort. אבל היכא דטרח בטל ברובא. Aval
Heicha d'Tarach Batel B'Ruba. But when you did exert effort, maybe it
does transform the old stuff. Now why does your exerting effort matter?
Let's first understand what the difference is. One case is the onion
was planted and it continued to grow naturally, right? It grew from
the sixth year into the seventh year. So then we'll say the
new stuff is שמיטה Shmita not the old stuff. The old stuff
doesn't get transformed, the old stuff remains sixth year, the new stuff
becomes שמיטה. Shmita. That's דלא טרח, d'Lo Tarach, it just all happened
on its own. But let's take another case. Dov, pay attention because
this is what you say. Okay, you actually went ahead and you
took grain or onions or whatever it was you had from that
you took תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Ma'asrot from, and you went ahead and
you planted them, קטרח, K'Tarach, you consciously did something to this stuff
that was היתר Heter and you planted it and now it continues
to grow. There maybe it does transform the old stuff. Why? Because
the fact that you did something to it, it wasn't just a
continuation of the process. You did something to it, transforms its identity.
As Dov said, you've turned it from vegetable into seed. Look at
what the way the ר"ן Ran explains it. He says,
the ר"ן Ran says like this.
The line that starts with the word לביטולי, L'Vatulei, it's one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, I think ten lines down
in the narrow lines of the ר"ן. Ran. He says like this.
He says, הני מילי היכא דלא טרח לביטולי. Hani Mili Heicha d'Lo
Tarach L'Vatulei.
That's when you didn't do anything to change its status, like the
onion continued to grow from year six to seven. אבל היכא דטרח,
Aval Heicha d'Tarach, but when you did some effort, כי האי גוונא
דליט... K'Hai Gavna d'Lit... of onions, you took this one unit of
onions שזרע בקרקע shezara bakarka that you planted it in the ground,
עשו גידולים, asu gidulim, the new stuff comes ומבטלין עיקר לגמרי um'vatlin
ikkar legamrei and completely transforms the original, even turns היתר heter into
איסור. issur. How could it turn היתר heter into איסור? issur? ולא
תיקשי לי אמאי דקא V'lo tikshi li amai d'ka now, one
minute, hold on, I thought he had a line here. One minute,
no,
he didn't say it. Somebody else explained, hold on one minute.
Maybe it was תוספות. Tosafot. Somebody explained it the way דוב Dov
was. One minute.
Wait a second, תוספות Tosafot says
about the בצל, batzal, בבצל דטרח
בגידולין.
be-vatzal d'tarach
be-gidulin.
Yeah,
alright,
I'm not seeing it. Somebody I thought said exactly the point that
דוב Dov was saying, maybe I just thought it in my head.
Okay, but that it seems to be that the answer of this
גמרא, Gemara, maybe it was on a different part of the גמרא,
Gemara, it seems to be that the answer of this גמרא Gemara
is exactly that point, that how much do we say that we
can transform the identity and even make something היתר heter into איסור?
issur? If you have completely redefined it, you have taken it and
you've planted it, it's not just grown, there's not just more. If
it's just more, then the original stuff doesn't become אסור, assur, it
remains היתר. heter. But if you've done something to it, you've completely
redefined its identity, that's a very different story. Okay, and there the
גמרא Gemara says maybe that case actually the היתר heter would transform
into איסור. issur. Okay, so let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues.
ועל כלהו שמעתא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל אלא דלא קטרח. V'al kulehu
sham'ata d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ella d'lo ka-tarach. Maybe this question, can
the איסור issur transform the היתר? heter? And רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, only the new stuff is אסור.
assur. Maybe that's only when there was no effort and it all
sort of happened naturally, so the איסור issur remains איסור issur and
the היתר heter remains היתר. heter. אבל היכא דקטרח, Aval heicha d'ka-tarach,
but if you actually exerted this effort, as it were, and it's
not just because you worked hard but it means you actively did
something new to the object and you planted it, then maybe בטל
ברובא, batel beruba, then maybe the whole object's identity does get transformed
and even the היתר heter turns into איסור. issur. Okay, and that
would actually be in that one case, in my case of the
מזוזה mezuzah getting mixed up, the מזוזה mezuzah doesn't become כשר kasher
just because it got mixed up in a lot of other כשר
kasher מזוזות. mezuzot. But here the whole thing does actually transform because
you've redefined its entire identity.
Because you planted in the soil, it redefines, because it gets more
nutrition than if it was just left on top.
Oh, that depends on how you explain that onion case. But I'd
rather explain it not about that but more about the fact that
it's, you know, that you've done something different to redefine its entire
identity, exactly along the line that דוב Dov was saying, like it
stops being, you know, a produce and it turned into seed and
sort of its identity became different. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. וכל היכא דקטרח בטל ברובא? V'chol heicha d'ka-tarach batel
beruba? You tell me every time you exert this effort, you know,
ביטול bittul would apply and redefine its identity in this way that
you're describing? והרי ליטרא מעשר טבל דקטרח? V'harei litra maaser tevel d'ka-tarach?
How about that case we had before, if you remember, where you
had that case of that unit of מעשר maaser that was טבל,
tevel, that didn't have תרומת מעשר terumat maaser taken from it, דקתני,
d'katni, and there we don't have ביטול, bittul, right? ועושה ליטרא מעשר
מעשר על מקום אחר לפי חשבון. V'osa litra maaser maaser al makom
acher lefi cheshbon. And there it said, so I don't know if
you can remember this one from yesterday, it's very complicated because we
had a lot of contradictory cases. But although this one case of
the one unit that you plant, that you took תרומות ומעשרות terumot
u'maasrot and then the nine units grow and we say it's like
ten new units and we do say ביטול, bittul, we didn't by
the case of the מעשר maaser of טבל, tevel, we said the
opposite. We said you had one unit of מעשר טבל, maaser tevel,
you planted it, new stuff grew, we said that original unit of
מעשר טבל maaser tevel retains its old status and doesn't become בטל.
batel. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says that doesn't work. You actively
planted it, new stuff grew, why there did it retain its old
status? So why didn't it not get transformed? So the גמרא Gemara
says, no. שאני גבי מעשר, shani gabei maaser, there it's different. אמר
קרא, amar kra, the verse says, עשר תעשר את כל תבואת זרעך.
aser taser et kol tevuat zar'echa. You should take מעשר maaser on
all of the planting of your seeds. So your seeds means the
normal types of things people plant. דהתירא זרעי אינשי, de-hetra zari inshi,
normal people plant like, you know, היתר heter stuff, stuff that they've
taken תרומות ומעשרות trumot u-maasrot from. איסורא לא זרעי אינשי, issura lo
zari inshi,
and people don't plant stuff that they haven't taken תרומות ומעשרות trumot
u-maasrot from. So basically, meaning it's getting very complicated, I didn't mean
to tell you that. Okay. So there's a lot of contradictions here
about whether you say ביטול bitul when new stuff grows. So in
the one case that we started with today, you planted a unit
you took תרומות ומעשרות trumot u-maasrot from, it continued to grow. A,
we said ביטול. bitul. Not only do we say ביטול, bitul, we
said ביטול bitul that even the old stuff that was מותר mutar
became טבל. tevel. We said that even היתר, heter, ביטול bitul even
makes היתר heter into איסור. issur. Okay, and that was like an
amazing idea and we said well, maybe that's a very special case
because you actively replanted it and that gave it a new status.
Okay. But now the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, but we've got
another case, almost exactly the same where we don't say ביטול. bitul.
You took a unit of מעשר maaser that was טבל tevel that
didn't have תרומות ומעשרות trumot u-maasrot taken from it, it wasn't totally
fixed grain, you planted it, it continued to grow, you actively planted
it, and we say that original unit of מעשר maaser still remains.
So it's almost exactly the same, why is it different? And the
גמרא Gemara basically quotes a פסוק pasuk to say, like it's exactly
the same. One case is if a unit of grain that's completely
fixed that's planted and grows, okay, and we say the original unit
actually lost its original identity. And then we have a unit of
grain that's מעשר maaser of טבל tevel that you plant and grows
and we say it retains its identity. What's the difference? And the
גמרא Gemara basically quotes a פסוק pasuk to say that the פסוק
pasuk is assuming that you're planting היתר heter grain. And that's when
you're planting היתר heter grain, then it says that we look at
everything as your new produce. But when you plant איסור issur grain,
which is a very unusual thing to do, you can't basically change
its identity. If you do the natural thing, getting back to Dov's
point, you're basically treating it like seed. Well, when do we say
you get to treat it like seed and you get to treat
this as something completely new that just grew? When you do the
natural thing. You take תרומות ומעשרות trumot u-maasrot off your old stuff,
you take some of those seeds and you replant them and they
grow, then we say that everything that comes now is new stuff.
But if you haven't finished with your old stuff, if you haven't
taken תרומות ומעשרות trumot u-maasrot and it still was אסור, assur, some
of your old stuff and you planted it, you don't get to
say well now it's just seed and this is just all new
stuff. No, that was something that normally is not planted, so its
identity doesn't get to become transformed and it retains its old identity,
and therefore that's a case where ביטול bitul does not apply.
There's something basic about that last case that I'm missing because if
I take טבל tevel seed and I plant it, yep, and then
that entire field grows, new produce, right, is not all that produce
טבל? tevel? No, because there's been no change in identity.
Of course there's been a change in
identity, because
it's untithed, no,
but that's everything we've been talking about is גידולים. gidulim. The new
stuff that grows doesn't take on the status of the old stuff.
But
if
I have a field,
forget about planting טבל tevel seed, I just have a field that
grew produce, I haven't tithed it yet. Isn't all that produce טבל?
tevel? Yes. So I've taken טבל, tevel, I've put it in my
field, it's now new produce, everything's
טבל.
tevel. Yes, but the importance about saying that you still have the
old טבל tevel there is that you have to take like תרומות
ומעשרות trumot u-maasrot based on its original seed instead of the whole
of the produce.
You're right. Like the new stuff is new טבל tevel but it
also has an old טבל tevel there that's still going on. Not
טבל tevel through that seed. Right. You're right. So the new טבל
tevel that's coming up but there's still the old טבל tevel that
has to be addressed. All right, we will actually finish this tomorrow.
Thank you.